{
  "reference_number": "11389",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a goal to reach net zero emissions by the second half of the century and the Climate Change Commission advises on the specific target for the Government to set later",
      "answer_index": 11,
      "notes": "The name of this Carbon Zero Bill demonstrates that the proponents of the bill have no knowledge or understanding of elementary\n\n science. Carbon is a base element, a major part of all plants, grass, trees, animals, mankind and a major part of our soils. If the Bill is\n referring to Carbon Dioxide, then again, the proponents of the bill have no knowledge or understanding of elementary science.\n Carbon dioxide is an inert, odourless, tasteless very minor trace gas in the atmosphere. CO2 is a tiny portion of the atmosphere at\n\n 0.04% or 405 ppm of the atmosphere, manmade CO2 is just 3% of total CO2 or 12 ppm. Carbon dioxide is the basis of all life on\n earth. Historic climate cycles are ignored with the claims that human related activities are emitting greenhouse gases that is\n\n increasing the average global temperature at an accelerated rate compared to historical temperatures. There is no the data to back\n this claim, only the IPCC computer models – all have been wrong. The Royal Society of NZ, Professor James Renwick, Dairy NZ and\n Minister James Shaw cannot provide any data that proves the claims of accelerated global temperature increase are caused by\n\n mankind."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Carbon Dioxide - Reducing net carbon dioxide emissions to zero by 2050",
      "answer_index": 13,
      "notes": "The “PC ETS agenda” to date is to only account for gross agricultural emissions. All farmers know that growing grass and crops\n sequesters carbon dioxide during the process of photosynthesis and this must be accounted for. To do otherwise is fraudulent. All\n\n discussions must be on net agricultural emissions. There are 4 reasons for agricultural methane must be excluded from the ETS • A\n steady state of methane emissions are offset by photosynthesis growing grass and crops. • Agricultural emissions must be\n accounted for on a net emissions basis. • Water vapour is the dominant greenhouse gas at 10,000 ppm of the atmosphere, CO2 is\n\n 405 ppm of the atmosphere, Methane is 1.8 ppm of the atmosphere, livestock emissions are only 17% of methane emissions which\n equals 0.306 ppm – a very tiny portion. • Any warming effect by methane has already been covered by the dominant greenhouse gas\n – water vapour Methane is a short-lived greenhouse gas. Molecules emitted into the atmosphere last on average about 12 years\n\n before being broken down into other gases, CO2 & water vapour. However, somewhat counter-intuitively, the carbon dioxide does\n not contribute to warming – if the methane has come from agriculture. This is because the methane has its origin in the grass eaten\n\n by the animal – grass that grew by taking carbon dioxide out of the atmosphere. This carbon dioxide has simply been recycled.” From\n the Parliamentary Commissioner for the Environment"
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "There must only be domestic emission reductions, any suggestion that overseas international carbon units be used is just fraud,\n they cannot make any difference to total world emissions. Any possible use reinforces what a \"fantasy world\" this bill is."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Science is never settled, there are thousands of scientific papers that challenge every aspect of this bill. Our overview of climate\n science is framed through four statements: 1. The climate is always changing; changes like those of the past half-century are\n common in the geologic record, driven by powerful natural phenomena 2. Human influences on the climate are a small (1%)\n\n perturbation to natural energy flows 3. It is not possible to tell how much of the modest recent warming can be ascribed to human\n influences 4. There have been no detrimental changes observed in the most salient climate variables and today’s projections of\n future changes are highly uncertain We offer supporting evidence for each of these statements drawn almost exclusively from the\n\n Climate Science Special Report (CSSR) issued by the US government in November, 2017 or from the Fifth Assessment Report (AR5)\nissued in 2013-14 by the UN’s Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change or from the refereed primary literature. From a paper by\n\nHapper, Koonin, Lindzen."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "See notes point 4 The IPCC projections are 1° C of warming 1980-2018, this is what all policy decisions are being made on but the\nreal- world temperatures from the balloon and satellite measurements only 0.21° C June2018. IPCC all wrong. Sea level is steady at\n\n1.4 mm per year, 11.2 cm by 2100 The latest satellite temperature for June 2018 is +0.21° C since 1980 – 0.055° C per decade. The\nIPCC prediction was 0.34° C per decade. Where is the problem? The main points from the NOAA web site, toolkit/basics • Water\nvapour is the predominant Greenhouse Gas • Water vapour absorbs infrared radiation • The sun ultimately drives the climate • Plants\n\nremove large amounts of CO2 from the atmosphere."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - each incoming Government should have the option to review the third budget in the sequence",
      "answer_index": 14,
      "notes": "The science is never settled"
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The accounting of agricultural emissions is total fraud, only gross emissions are accounted for. There are 4 reasons for agricultural\n\nmethane must be excluded from the ETS • A steady state of methane emissions are offset by photosynthesis growing grass and\ncrops. • Agricultural emissions must be accounted for on a net emissions basis. • Water vapour is the dominant greenhouse gas at\n\n10,000 ppm of the atmosphere, CO2 is 405 ppm of the atmosphere, Methane is 1.8 ppm of the atmosphere, livestock emissions are\nonly 17% of methane emissions which equals 0.306 ppm – a very tiny portion. • Any warming effect by methane has already been\n\ncovered by the dominant greenhouse gas – water vapour It is pleasing to read there is some rethinking from Professor David Frame\nand his colleagues over accounting for agricultural methane emissions, this is what I have been promoting for a long time – net\nemissions for agriculture."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The science is not settled. There is no proof for this requirement. Yes, we have Climate Change but the climate has always changed\n\nover the past centuries and always will continue to change, nothing new in this. Considerable parts of NZ are flood plains, protected\nby stop banks. Yes we have recent global warming, from the Medieval Warm Period, 900-1200 the earth cooled 2° C to the Little Ice\n\nAge, 1600-1800, it has warmed 0.81° C since 1850 as we recover from the Little Ice age, nothing exceptional about this. This is\nNatural variability. Or would you prefer the climatic conditions of the little ice age?"
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "See note, point 8"
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The government must provide some honest science to back up the extravagant claims that “human related activities are emitting\ngreenhouse gases that is increasing the average global temperature at an accelerated rate compared to historical temperatures” It\n\nmust also provide data to back up the claims of more floods, more storms and more droughts. As noted in 5 above there has only\nbeen 0.21° C of warming over the last 38 years"
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The UK commission is a complete failure. Their targets will not be met, the UK has a electricity crisis, a 25% increase in prices for\n\nelectricity, a generation short fall. At present the UK is calling for tenders for new gas generation but there are funding problems."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "The ETS is a complete failure, it cannot achieve any useful reduction in emissions, it only adds costs for the NZ consumer. If there are\nnew products or services that are economical to provide they will be adopted without the ETS. The ETS is only supported by those\n\nwho can benefit \"clipping the ticket\" by trading in carbon units"
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "From present policies the Climate Commissioners will only be appointed from persons who have a conflict of interest. There is only a\nconsensus among those who work for governments or their agencies. Any person working for the government or a government\n\nagency (including universities, research institutions, NIWA) has a conflict of interest as they are not allowed to speak out against the\n“PC agenda of Climate Change” There is a vast amount of independent science that challenges every aspect of this bill as it is based\non government ideology and green fantasy, it does not contain creditable science or achieveable solutions. There must be some\n\ntruely independent commisioners, independent of any government agency who will provide a wide range of true climate science\ninstead of the narrow view of government ideology that has been presented to date. The climate is much more complex than just\n\ncarbon dioxide and a tiny bit of methane."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, we have Climate Change but the climate has always changed over the past centuries and always will continue to change,\n\nnothing new in this. Considerable parts of NZ are flood plains, protected by stop banks. Yes we have recent global warming, from the\nMedieval Warm Period, 900-1200 the earth cooled 2° C to the Little Ice Age, 1600-1800, it has warmed 0.81° C since 1850 as we\n\nrecover from the Little Ice age, nothing exceptional about this. This is Natural variability. Or would you prefer the climatic conditions of\nthe little ice age? Yes we can only adapt to the continuing changing climate. Claiming that reducing carbon dioxide by 3% will stabilise\nthe climate is just fraud. CO2 has very little effect on the climate."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, we have Climate Change but the climate has always changed over the past centuries and always will continue to change,\n\nnothing new in this. Considerable parts of NZ are flood plains, protected by stop banks. Yes we have recent global warming, from the\nMedieval Warm Period, 900-1200 the earth cooled 2° C to the Little Ice Age, 1600-1800, it has warmed 0.81° C since 1850 as we\n\nrecover from the Little Ice age, nothing exceptional about this. This is Natural variability. Or would you prefer the climatic conditions of\nthe little ice age? Yes we need an adaption plan but it must be based on real data, not the extravagant claims made to date."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes co-operation is needed but it must be based on real data, not the extravagant claims made to date."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The name of this Carbon Zero Bill demonstrates that the proponents of the bill have no knowledge or understanding of elementary\nscience. Carbon is a base element, a major part of all plants, grass, trees, animals, mankind and a major part of our soils. If the Bill is\n\nreferring to Carbon Dioxide, then again, the proponents of the bill have no knowledge or understanding of elementary science.\nCarbon dioxide is an inert, odourless, tasteless very minor trace gas in the atmosphere. CO2 is a tiny portion of the atmosphere at\n\n0.04% or 405 ppm of the atmosphere, manmade CO2 is just 3% of total CO2 or 12 ppm. Historic climate cycles are ignored with the\nclaims that human related activities are emitting greenhouse gases that is increasing the average global temperature at an\n\naccelerated rate compared to historical temperatures. There is no the data to back this claim, only the IPCC computer models – all\nhave been wrong. The Royal Society of NZ, Professor James Renwick, Dairy NZ and Minister James Shaw cannot provide any data that\nproves the claims of accelerated global temperature increase are caused by mankind. The claim that reducing manmade CO2\n\nemissions that are 3% of total CO2 in the atmosphere will stabilise the climate are just fraud. The climate much more complex than\njust CO2 and methane. Yes, we have Climate Change but the climate has always changed over the past centuries and always will\n\ncontinue to change, nothing new in this. Considerable parts of NZ are flood plains, protected by stop banks. Yes we have recent\nglobal warming, from the Medieval Warm Period, 900-1200 the earth cooled 2° C to the Little Ice Age, 1600-1800, it has warmed\n\n0.81° C since 1850 as we recover from the Little Ice age, nothing exceptional about this. This is Natural variability. Or would you prefer\nthe climatic conditions of the little ice age? In the AR5 IPCC report their scientists admitted that the world is warming more slowly than\n\npredicted, the IPCC predicted a warming of 0.34° C per decade but it is only 0.11° C. Ignored. The Carbon Cycle is the fundamental\npathway ahead but it is completely ignored. Repeatedly it is demonstrated that there is no understanding of the carbon cycle and\ncarbon dioxide’s vital role in all life on earth. Water vapour the dominant greenhouse gas is 10,000 ppm of the atmosphere, CO2 is\n\n405 ppm of the atmosphere, manmade CO2 is 3% or 12 ppm, Methane is 1.8 ppm of the atmosphere, livestock emissions are only\n17% of methane emissions which equals 0.306 ppm A steady state of methane is off-set by CO2 sequestration growing grass and\n\ncrops. Basic physics – you can only emit what is sequestered. Agricultural emissions must be accounted for on a net emission basis.\nNZ has 3% of the worlds dairy cows, what happens to the worlds other 97% ? No other country in the world is stupid enough to tax\n\nagriculture, their food producers. NZ emissions are very small, only 0.17% of global emissions There are 1600 coal fired power\nstations being constructed or planned China, presently 13.5%, says it will double by 2030, India, presently 6.8% says it will triple by\n2030 Electricity. There will be big increase in demand for electricity by a growing population, EVs and other industrial electrification.\n\nMore hydro? More wind and solar are very expensive because they are very intermittent and need an equal amount of back up\ngeneration or face blackouts. There are no proposals or cost/ benefit analysts. It is absolutely essential that our present fossil fuel\n\nbackup generation be retained for security of supply. Lessons must be learnt from Australia, UK and Germany the problems they are\nhaving attempting to move to wind generation as well as the 25% increase in power prices their consumers are facing. NZ must\n\nfacture in the huge transitional import costs of a new transport fleet, huge costs for additional power generation at the same time our\nmain export base is restrained. In 2017 NZ Current account deficit was - $7.7 billion, that is, NZ imports $7.7 billion more in goods and\n\nservices than it exports. How are we going to pay for all the additional imports required? Reducing NZ’s emissions of 0.17% will\nreduce global temperatures by how much? = 0 N Z is very small export dependent country, our industries and exporters cannot\nsurvive the extra costs that will be imposed by this bill that their overseas competitors do not have. New Zealand does not the\n\ntechnologies or the financial resources available to meet the impossible targets of this bill, which would make no difference to the\nglobal climte."
    }
  ]
}
